Hi,

To give you a brief introduction, I am a seasoned and dynamic Sales and Business Development Specialist with over 14 years of Techno-Commercial professional experience spread across Telecom, IT Services and Media in both the international and domestic markets. Presently I am based in Mumbai. My last full-time assignment has been as the AVP - Sales and Business Development with Tanla Solutions Ltd., wherein I was responsible for working closely with the company management and heading the complete Sales Strategy/Execution, Business Development, Client Relationships as well as the brand creation, entire P&L responsibility for the pan India business across all the three segments; Telecom, Media and Enterprise.

Over the past years, apart from India I have also traveled extensively and covered geographies globally, successfully tapping and opening up new markets, creating brand presence, negotiating and closing direct deals, setting up business in regions including US, Europe, APAC (Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Australia), SAARC (Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan), Latin America (Mexico, Brazil), Middle East and Africa, spanning through the entire sales cycle right from the initial lead development to agreement closure, handholding to the account/project teams followed up with the complete business and revenue generation ownership/maximization thereon. I have had an excellent proven record of client consulting, end to end sales cycle management, negotiations and coordination with cross functional teams and a very high standard of client relationship and internal team setup and management to leverage the best interests of my organizations.

Kindly do let me know if you feel we can synergize and if I could get an opportunity to bring some added value to this fitting role in your organization. I have attached my resume alongwith.

Best Regards,

Milind Raikar +91 9833930783

MILIND RAIKAR

GSM: +91-9833930783 E-mail: milindraikar@gmail.com

Curriculum Vitae

OBJECTIVE

Seeking a challenging position that can help me in the purpose of demonstrating my hardworking and entrepreneurial abilities along with my creative as well as innovative skills, thereby contributing to the benefit and success of the organization that I am working for.

PROFILE

An experienced Telecom professional with excellent Sales, Business Development and Key Account Management skills having 14 years of overall professional experience specializing in both the Techno and Commercial business aspects coupled with excellent communication and organization skills as well as a strong sense of responsibility. Highly self motivated, result-oriented and efficient with the readiness and ability to learn new skills very quickly. Capable of adapting and taking quick decisions and finding solutions as per the changing requirements of the hour, in combination with a perfect management of the resources.

RESPONSIBILITIES AND KEY STRENGTH AREAS

Sales & Business Development

- Develop and execute Business Strategies, Pre and Post Sales Plans, Budgeting, Forecasting, Pipeline Building and Management, Brand Positioning, Creation and Building, Product Conceptualization / Marketing, Presentations, Proposals, Contract Negotiations, Deal Closures, Agreements, Customer Acquisition / Retention, Partner Evaluations and Alliances, etc. for both domestic as well as international markets
- Demonstrated ability to work across geographies and build/market products and solutions starting with an innate understanding of customer needs.
- Cross-functional leadership in Revenue Generation, P&L projections and accountability, Customer Retention
- Excellent customer acquisition and convincing skills across the stakeholder hierarchy

Key Account Management

- Excellent client consulting skills and strong relationship management
- Managing multiple key client accounts and entire businesses and revenues within
- Reporting on Projections, Financials, Business Plans, Resources, Risks
- Planning, monitoring and control of accounts
- Hiring, mentoring and managing team members
- Proactive identification of issues and necessary action for the same

On-Site Coordination

Driving work at the offshore location by closely interacting with the business, product and delivery units.

TECHNICAL SPECIALIZATION SKILLS

- Proficient in Proposals and Presentations
- Extensive knowledge of Products and Technologies

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Role : Independent Consultant - IT/Telecom

(April 2012 - Present)

Responsibilities:

- Plan and direct complete sales and business development strategy for SMEs
- Brand creation, positioning and building
- Strategic Alliances and Partnerships
- New customer acquisitions and revenue generation

Organization: Tanla Solutions Ltd.

Role: AVP – Sales and Business Development – Reporting to the CMD (October 2010 – March 2012)

Responsibilities:

- Heading the entire sales strategy and execution across the three verticals; Telecom Platforms/Products, Media Services and Enterprise Solutions, pan India.
- Generating sales funnel and acquisition of new accounts and strategic partnerships across verticals
- Positioning of the organization branding throughout the industry
- Developing strategies for revenue generation/enhancement and retention of existing key customers along with penetration into new accounts and converting competition revenues
- Work closely with the Presales, Product/Development and Branding teams to help identify, develop and customize products/solutions
- Relationship building and management, proposals, deal closures at techno and commercial levels, agreements, etc.
- Responsible for setting up the first outside HQ Sales office in Mumbai, putting together and managing the PAN India sales force personnel team from scratch to have a strong focus over the customers and accounts
- Revenue and P&L responsibility, budgeting and forecasting, management reporting
- Scope of Geographies/Customers covered: India, APAC, SAARC

Organization: IMI mobile Pvt. Ltd.

Role: Sr. Manager/AVP – Sales and Business Development – Reporting to the Sr. Vice President, Sales (September 2009 – October 2010)

Responsibilities:

- Driving business by tapping and building new markets, opening up new customers, managing sales strategies and new business development for Telcos and OEMs in India and APAC
- Taking the existing complete portfolio suite of products, platforms and managed services to existing and new customers
- · Leveraging existing business opportunities with customers as well as creating new opportunities
- Relationship building and management, proposals, deal closures at techno and commercial levels, agreements, etc.
- Revenue and P&L responsibility, budgeting and forecasting, reporting
- Scope of Geographies/Customers covered: India, APAC, SAARC, Africa

Organization: MoFirst Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

Role : Head of Sales & Business Development

(June 2009 - August 2009)

Responsibilities:

• Plan and direct complete sales and business development strategies for both international and domestic markets

- Selling products and technology services to customers including Telecom Operators, OEMs, Enterprises, and System Integrators
- Establishing partners and driving partnership initiatives
- Brand building
- Relationship building and management, proposals, deal closures at techno and commercial levels, agreements, etc.
- Revenue and P&L responsibility, budgeting and forecasting
- Scope of Geographies/Customers covered: India, APAC, SAARC, US, Europe

Organization: OnMobile Global Ltd.

Role: Sr. Manager – International Business Development/Sales and Key Account Manager (for Nokia) – Reporting to the Head of Sales and Marketing (September 2006 – May 2009)

Responsibilities:

- Tapping and building new markets and managing sales strategies and new business development for both international (APAC, SAARC, ME, Australia, Latin America) and domestic markets. Have successfully opened up new customers internationally and in a significant number of these cases first customers in APAC (Singapore, Malaysia, Indonesia, Thailand, Australia), SAARC (Nepal, Bangladesh, Pakistan), ME, Latin America (Mexico, Brazil).
- Selling platforms, solutions and managed services to new and existing customers including Telecom Operators and OEMs
- Heading and managing the entire business for the complete **Nokia** account (India and APAC) and cultivating the engagement by creating new business opportunities along with revenue generation and maximization.
- Relationship building and management, proposals, deal closures at techno and commercial levels, agreements, etc.
- Revenues and P&L responsibility, budgeting and forecasting, reporting
- Scope of Geographies/Customers covered: India, APAC, SAARC, Australia, Africa, ME, LATAM, Middle East

Organization: BrickRed Technologies (ISO 9001-2000 Certified)

Role: Program Manager / Key Account Manager – Reporting to the CEO (September 2004 – August 2006)

Responsibilities:

- New business development specially targeting US and European customers
- Extensively involved in Pre-Sales on both the Techno and Commercial fronts
- Key account and customer management, revenue responsibility and maximization from acquired accounts, budgeting and forecasting
- Requirements elicitation and project analysis, scoping, estimations, revenues
- Monitoring and controlling of the project and process control, resource building and management, deliverables, quality considerations, risk management and project invoicing.
- Scope of Geographies/Customers covered: US, Europe, India

Organization: Recreate Solutions (Corpus)

Role: Project Manager – Reporting to the President – Operations (August 2003 – September 2004)

Responsibilities:

- Managing all pre-sales activities and SPOC for all client interactions related to complete business requirements
 gathering and project development for interactive television (i-TV) applications running on set-top boxes for leading
 television channels like i-TV, UKTV, Grenada TV in UK and Europe
- On-site coordination from the client site with the project teams in India

- Extensively involved in Project Management with Project Analysis, Scoping, Planning, Estimations, Design, Development, Managing Deliveries and Quality, driving new business from existing accounts
- Monitoring and controlling of the project and process control, resource building and management, deliverables, quality considerations, risk management and project invoicing.
- Scope of Geographies/Customers: India, US, Europe, Canada

Organization: Paradox Systems Pvt. Ltd. (Group Company of Reliance Infocomm Ltd.)

Role: Project/Team Leader (April 2002 - August 2003)

Responsibilities:

- Extensively involved in the design, development and deployment of wireless applications and a range of user interactive voice applications using the Voice XML Technology for Reliance India Mobile Cellular Services across a wide range of handsets including smart phones for the launch of their services
- Extensively involved in the design, development and deployment of wireless applications for Reliance India Mobile Cellular Services across a wide range of handsets for the launch of their services and working in close conjunction with the technical experts from IBM and Nortel Networks
- Presented a demonstration of the Voice Portal to the top corporates of Reliance Industries Limited from all over the country during the launch of the RIM cellular services

Organization: National Institute of Information Technology.

Role : Software Developer/Team Leader

(August 1999 - March 2002)

Responsibilities:

- Worked on development related projects related to various domains including Airlines, Banking, Education/E-Learning Corporate Virtual Universities, etc.
- Involved in all phases of the development i.e. designing, coding and testing, product documentation

EDUCATION

Diploma in E-Commerce and E-Business Technologies, National Institute of Information Technology, Mumbai

American College of Computer and Information Sciences, Alabama, United States

Correspondence Degree for Bachelor of Science with major in Information Systems

D.G. Ruparel College of Science, Commerce and Arts, Mumbai, India

• Secured an aggregate of 86% in the Science Stream of the Higher Secondary School Certificate Board Examination with Computer Science as the vocational subjects

Modern English School, Mumbai, India

Secured an aggregate of 91% in the Secondary School Certificate Board Examination

ADDITIONAL QUALIFICATIONS & CERTIFICATIONS

- Certified Dale Carnegie Sales Advantage Program Professional
- Certification in Astrowix Project Management Program

PERSONAL DETAILS

Date of birth : 13/12/1978
Marital status : Married
Nationality : Indian

Passport : Valid till 08/09/2021